- "Previously on The mentalist..."
- No!
"We believe the assailant
is the same person"
"that killed attorney Osvaldo Ardiles"
"and former California Bureau
of Investigation agent J.J. Laroche."
Good to see you, guys.
Just got word that the FBI
has officially hired you
as consultants for the case.
You're the ones who first found out
we were being tracked.
You know this case
better than anybody.
- Anything on the other seven suspects?
- A few leads. No breakthroughs.
Which leaves us with Haibach.
Hey. I fell asleep.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I just wanted to check in.
I'm out having
a drink with the guys.
What happened with Hutten?
It's not him.
I'll explain later.
You go back to bed.
- You having fun?
- Yeah. Yeah, I am.
- I'm glad. It's good for you.
- Thank you.
- "I love you, babe. You know that, right?"
- I love you, too.
- Okay, I'll see you soon.
- Good night.
Well, she agreed with you.
She said I should be out having
a drink with you guys
said it would be good for me.
- She's a smart woman.
- Yeah. Yeah, she is.
I'm a lucky man.
She's the best.
A price above rubies.
- To Grace.
- To Grace. Thank you.
You know, Grace and I, we, uh...
Oh, we always thought
that you and Lisbon would...
you know, get together.
- Jane and Lisbon... yeah, right.
- I'm just saying.
Remember when
you bought her a pony?
Yes, I do.
I do remember that.
I wonder what happened to it.
Okay, two more lone stars
and a club soda.
And the man at the pool table
wants another game with you.
Well, can't he see
I'm here with my friends?
He seemed pretty determined
said he'd make it double or nothing.
Go and take the man's money.
I got to get back to my wife.
It's been a pleasure.
- Good night. Wish me luck.
- Good luck.
Let's get something to eat.
Yeah, I think I saw
a drive-through on the way over.
They had chimichangas.
Same old Rigsby.
"You ever thought about coming
to work at the FBI?"
"You kidding me?"
"Been daydreaming about it
for the past six months."
So why not join?
- You think they'd have me?
- I know they would.
Abbott's the one
that wanted me to ask you...
Both of you, actually.
Really? Both of us?
I don't know.
It's a pretty 24/7 type of gig.
Someone's got to look
after the kids.
You should talk about it with Grace.
The offer's there.
Nice. Okay.
Well, you want to come up for a drink
discuss it with Grace?
No. Best you two
talk about it alone.
Right. Yeah,
you're probably right.
Hey. Why's the door to your room open?
I don't know.
Grace?
Grace? Grace?!
Keys are still on the table.
So is her wallet.
There's a perfectly reasonable
explanation for this, right?
- Please tell me there's one.
- Don't jump to conclusions.
- What are you doing?
- Calling her cell.
Where are you, Grace?
Hello?
Is anybody there?
Hello!
Rigsby and Jane are with a team
combing through the motel room
but we've got nothing yet.
there's about a thousand
different fingerprints
and DNA
all over everything.
I hate hotel rooms.
How's Wylie doing
with the camera footage
that we pulled
from around town?
He's traced her whereabouts
before she got to the motel.
Anything useful?
- No.
- Well, what else?
An S.U.V. leaving the area
of the motel
at the estimated time
of Grace Van Pelt's abduction.
Was he able to get
a license plate from it?
No.
All right, people, listen up.
We already know our prime suspect...
Richard Haibach.
We were already looking at him
for the murders
of ex-CBI agent J.J. Laroche
and D.A. Osvaldo Ardiles.
Now Grace Van Pelt is gone.
Where?
We don't know.
But we're assuming
that Haibach is responsible.
Excuse me, agent Abbott?
We got a bolo out.
We alerted the media.
But Haibach has already slipped
our tail In Colorado.
He's in the wind.
He knows we're coming after him.
And he will not be easy to find.
Agent Abbott, there's someone
to see you.
But find him we will.
Whatever it takes, people.
Failure is not an option here.
Find Richard Haibach.
Agent Wylie, what do you need?
Well, there's a... There's a man
who came to reception downstairs.
- An agent's bringing him up.
- So?
The man says
he's Richard Haibach.
Go get Jane back here now.
Hello?!
Is anybody here?!
Hello, agent Lisbon, Mr. Jane.
Sit down, please.
Why are you here,
Mr. Haibach?
Is that some kind of joke?
I've been in fear of my life
since I learned you were
stalking me again.
We're not stalking you,
Mr. Haibach.
I knew the moment you started
asking questions about me
behind my back
to people at my job
that you were out to get me.
I already apologized
to you for that.
Oh, you apologized
but that didn't stop
your plotting, did it?
We just had
a few questions for you.
Really? So I'm not
your number-one suspect?
This a game?
No game, Mr. Jane.
I am, as I said,
in fear for my life.
Think about what you're doing.
These are people
I care a lot about.
Yes or no...
A warrant has been issued
for my arrest, hasn't it?
- How did you know about that?
- So one has.
I call that an execution order
a license to shoot me down
in the street like a dog.
So I'm here to prove my innocence
beyond any shadow of a doubt.
Do you have any knowledge
as to what's happened
to Grace Van Pelt?
No. I don't.
- How could I?
- Take a guess...for fun.
Okay. Sure.
I can make plenty of guesses
but that's all it is... guesses.
But...
Let's see.
I'd guess she was...
Somewhere far away,
out of the reach of your help
out of the reach
of anyone's help...
alone and trapped...
with time running out...
if I were to guess, I mean.
Showing up like this
is a bad sign.
90% of the time, it means
the victim's already dead.
Well, I don't see any reason
to jump to conclusions.
You've been through the Quantico
profiling courses, too.
His performative aspect suggests
that he's already killed her.
He's just here to gloat
when we find the body.
Where's my wife?!
Rigsby!
What have you done with her?!
Come on, please.
If you hurt her, I'll kill you!
You're an animal!
Hurt her?! Look at me!
What about me?!
- I'll kill you!
- No!
Stop! Not here!
I was tortured because you people
thought I deserved it and I did nothing!
I did nothing!
My thumb was cut off
because of you!
- You people are the animals!
- Sit down, Mr. Haibach.
Okay, Rigsby, Listen.
I understand how you're feeling
right now. Believe me.
But you are a father and you have
children you need to see grow up.
- Besides, I think she's still alive.
- You do?
Yes.
Haibach's revenge plan
was disrupted by Grace
when she broke
his phone hacks up.
He realized then
that it was only a matter of time
before we tracked him down.
This is him making
the best of the situation.
Then why did he come here?
To gloat and watch us squirm.
And he plans to make us
let him go when he's done.
We won't let him
get away with it.
I wonder if you'd mind telling us
where you've been
for the last 24 hours.
Do you own an S.U.V....
Maybe gray?
No, I don't.
But this is a video of me
on the bus from Denver to Austin.
This is my bus ticket.
And these are the names
of three of the other passengers
on the bus and the bus driver.
They can confirm I was on the bus
during the entire trip.
And in this envelope
is everything you need to know
about my whereabouts
during the time of the murders
of Osvaldo Ardiles
and J.J. Laroche.
It's tabulated and cross-referenced.
Now, my attorney is scheduled
to arrive, well, anytime now.
Okay, Haibach's attorney
is gonna be here at any second
and we have no reason
to hold him.
This is his alibi.
I want it turned inside out
and torn apart.
Find the holes
and see where they lead.
In any event,
the evidence suggests
that Haibach is working
with an accomplice.
Find out who that is...
Somebody he hangs out with
at work
somebody that he met
on the internet
old friend, new friend.
Find the accomplice.
And do it quickly.
We don't have the luxury of time.
Oh, damn it.
Okay, here's the bus route
from Denver to Austin.
How many miles is that?
Um... let me see.
It's a little over
916 miles.
"Daddy, are you coming home?"
Not for a little while longer, buddy.
You're having a good time
with your mom, though, right?
"I guess. She works a lot."
"Is Grace there?"
No. She's... she's not here right now.
"She always tells me a story
before my nap."
A story?
"About a nice bull
who has to go to the bull fight."
Ferdinand.
Well, he gets to go home.
- "And smell the flowers."
- Yeah.
And he's very happy,
sitting under a big tree.
"Yeah."
Okay, look, I...
I have to go, buddy.
We'll speak very soon, okay?
Daddy loves you.
- "Love you, too. Bye, dad."
- Bye, son.
Excuse me.
Hey.
Haibach's lawyer is here.
Abbott's gonna try and stall her
for as long as he can
but we're probably
gonna have to let Haibach go.
We don't have enough concrete
evidence to hold him on.
Okay.
Jane, whatever it takes.
Please. I'm begging you.
We have to get Grace back.
I should have been contacted
the moment my client
arrived at your offices.
Well, he came
on his own volition.
We simply met him
as he asked.
Well, I'd like to speak to my client alone.
Look at me. You know me.
You know what I am capable of.
So if you have done anything
to Grace Van Pelt
I am gonna make you pay.
Excuse me. The law says you
can't just charge in here...
Oh, don't you worry
about the law.
You need to worry
about me.
Is this man completely insane?
And no matter where you go
I will find you, and I will make you pay.
Agent Abbott, in all my years,
I have never witnessed...
- All right, that's enough, Jane.
- Okay.
See, what you don't understand
about me, Rich is I don't care.
I've got nothing to lose.
I've been playing
with the house money for years.
And if I go to prison for what
I do to you, I don't care.
- Okay, come on. That's enough.
- If your friend dies, it's your fault.
- That's enough.
- You can't blame me!
I had nothing to do with it...
Nothing at all!
- What in the hell were you doing?
- The unexpected.
Yeah, it was that.
Well, we want Haibach
out of his comfort zone
so we push him
to make a mistake.
Okay, now, we both know I give
you a lot of latitude
but you just criminally
threatened a suspect
in front of his lawyer
on video.
It's admissible in court.
He came here with a plan,
and we don't know what that plan is
but he does.
So he knows the pattern
in advance.
We need to break
that pattern.
Do you have a minute?
Just waiting for my client.
Knock yourself out.
We just need
a little more time.
Really?
My firm is already in the process
of getting
the depositions of the bus's
passengers and the driver.
We'll have them all
by this evening.
Richard Haibach's whereabouts
during the abduction of your associate
can be stated with absolute certainty.
You have no reason
to hold my client.
Not yet, but the reason is there.
Now, even you
have to see that.
He took her.
We all know that he did.
Then prove it.
Otherwise, you have to let my client go.
That's the way the law works.
He'll kill her if we let him go,
if he hasn't already.
Do you realize that?
Look, don't try
and make me feel guilty.
I've been doing this
a long time
and my job as a lawyer
is to defend my client.
That's why people pay me.
So you can give me
whatever sob story you want
but we both know
you've got nothing.
Whatever happens
is on your head.
That is inaccurate
unprofessional, and disrespectful.
I'm doing my job.
Don't make me do yours.
Hello?!
Is anybody out here?!
Anybody out here?!
Hey. Hey.
Hey!
Hey.
Are you okay?
- Do you have a phone? I just...
- Well, look, were you in an accident?
just need a phone.
Please, do you have a phone?
Okay, okay, okay.
Okay, here. Here it is.
Thank you.
- Is there coverage?
- I don't know.
It's kind of spotty out here.
You're half-frozen.
Where's your car?
Where's the police station?
Taos, I guess.
That's 45 minutes north of here.
Or there's a ranger station
about a half an hour south.
Where's the nearest phone?
Well, my cabin, I guess.
Okay, okay.
I need you to take me there.
Can you take me there? It's important.
Just take me there right now.
Yeah, yeah. All right.
Get in, get in, get in.
Okay.
Oh, you must be frozen.
Yeah.
I've looked into Haibach's known
associates. It's a short list.
He was a loner at work
and in his private life.
He's got an older sister named Hazel
that I haven't been able to contact.
I sent local P.D. to check her address.
Should be hearing soon.
Dubin knows we don't have enough
to charge Haibach.
We have to let him walk.
I'll tell Rigsby.
Keep him together, okay?
You think if I talk
to this lawyer woman to woman
it would have any effect?
Don't waste your time.
Okay, here we are.
Home sweet home.
Come on, darling,
let's get you inside.
- Get you something warm.
- Okay. Thanks.
Okay, now, mind those steps,
'cause those are slippery.
Hey, shut the door behind you.
Don't let the heat out.
Phone's in the bedroom.
I'll go get it.
- No electricity, huh?
- Oh, lord. Bless your heart. No.
The poles don't come out this far.
- Then how do you have a phone?
- I don't.
I lied.
Okay, kids, time's up.
Put your pencils down.
We're processing
your client right now.
I'll tell my car to pull around.
Okay, that's right.
Pull it tight.
Use your teeth.
Okay.
So you just stay here
and you don't cause trouble.
Richard's gonna know what to do
with you when he gets here.
Please, do you have
anything hot to drink?
I got some coffee
I can heat up.
That'd be great. Thanks.
And no tricks.
No tricks.
My name's Grace,
by the way.
Don't you try and make friends,
'cause I'm not stupid.
Okay. Sorry.
Richard's your brother,
isn't he?
It was just the two of you,
wasn't it?
- No other sisters or brothers?
- Yep.
- You're older?
- Three years.
Something happened
when you were kids, didn't it?
Something bad.
Richard had it
so hard growing up.
You people
didn't understand that.
It wasn't his fault.
What was so hard?
Our mother run away
left us both with a drunk.
And he did things
to Richard.
Things he shouldn't have.
Wasn't his fault.
I didn't protect him.
His big sister...
Didn't protect him.
You were just a little girl.
It's not your fault.
Don't you pretend sympathy.
You people are bad as my father...
What you did to Richard.
He wasn't hurting nobody,
but you pushed and you pushed.
And now, miss cutie pie,
it is you who's gonna be hurt.
'cause that's only fair.
"The next step will be
taking the FBI to court."
"We have grounds
for a strong suit."
Will they all lose their jobs?
Well, sure, but there's potential
for a large settlement, as well...
- Eight-figures large.
- I don't care about money.
I just want to make sure
Patrick Jane suffers.
I want him to suffer a lot.
Hey, you missed he on-ramp.
This is the wrong way.
No, you don't have to stop.
You can just take the next right.
Hello, again.
Haibach, counselor.
Jane and Rigsby
are missing.
We found Dubin's livery driver
locked up in a downstairs closet.
Sir, honestly, I didn't know
anything about this.
We had nothing
to do with it.
But we would have,
if they asked.
Now, I'm sure you
find that brave and noble
but it's not.
You're federal agents,
and I expect you to behave as such.
Otherwise, I have no use for you.
Now get out of my office.
Fischer.
Find them. Right now.
Get out.
Oh, you people are insane.
You're never gonna
get away with this.
Listen, he took my wife.
Whatever he gets, he deserves.
Now go.
Counselor.
Here.
You should probably think
about your choice of clients
on your little walk back to Austin.
Looks good.
I'm a mother, you know.
I have a baby girl.
Her name's Maddy.
Cut it out.
I don't want to hear about it.
We named her
after my grandmother.
Her name's really Madeleine
but she looks more
like a Maddy, you know?
She shouldn't have to grow up
without a mother, should she?
You just don't get it, do you?
This isn't about you.
This is about me and Richard.
Everybody has looked down on us.
It's like we were nothing.
But now they'll see.
Hazel and Richard are gonna
get the attention they deserve.
Hey.
Wait a minute.
What were you just doing?
Put your hands up.
Put 'em up!
Oh, you little bitch!
You were, oh, just making all nice.
And the whole time
you're just lying, lying, lying to me.
Aah! Hazel, that's too tight.
You're hurting me.
Well, that's what you deserve,
isn't it, you big liar?!
And you know what...
when Richard gets here
I'm gonna tell him all about this
and he's gonna be so mad.
You know what?
I don't want to hear
any more of your words!
Where is she?!
Where's my wife?
You're wasting your time.
- Where is she?!
- I won't tell you where she is.
You can kill me.
It won't make a difference.
- I'm gonna die! I'm gonna die!
- Whoa, whoa.
Does that change anything?
No! Stop! Stop!
Answer me.
Where is she?
Rigsby.
Where's my wife?!
Whoa, Rigsby! Calm down,
calm down. Just count to 10.
- Just count to 10. Count to 10.
- Where's my wife?
No, we don't
want to kill him.
We just want to make him talk.
I have a plan.
This isn't about
one of your plans.
See, you need to just stop
and just talk to me, okay?
Talk to me, Rigsby.
There's another way.
I'm gonna make him talk.
No, Rigsby.
No! No, Rigsby.
You don't want to do this.
I got no time
to play games here.
I want answers!
Answer me!
Where's my wife?!
Last chance!
Okay, you need
to let me handle this.
No, there's no time.
I have to find Grace.
You're gonna set fire to the only person
that can tell us where she is.
What is the point of that?
What is that gonna prove?
Drop something?
- No, don't.
- Drop the flare.
- Get rid of the flare!
- Okay, okay.
Give me your coat.
Put the vest in the trunk.
You, Jane, you're gonna drive.
Let's go.
Easy.
Man was curious
about his wife.
I'm gonna satisfy
that curiosity.
Get in.
They found Dubin
on old highway 29.
Maybe they're headed for hill country.
Haibach could have a place out there.
Yeah, I don't think so.
I've had agents searching
every inch of the state.
I think they're out of Texas.
I have an idea.
Maybe. New Mexico.
Up in the Sangre de Cristo mountains.
Why do you think that?
Well, I thought I'd try coming
from a different angle, you know?
'cause everyone kept saying
How Haibach was being
so careful and stuff.
So first I looked into where Haibach
was born and grew up.
Oh, let me guess...
New Mexico?
No, but he had grandparents there
spent time there as a child.
He liked it, returned whenever he could.
In fact, he wrote his thesis in college
on the pueblo people culture,
which is centered in New Mexico.
He... he didn't actually do too
well on the paper, actually...
We don't need to know that.
Oh, okay. Right.
So... so then I started looking
into his shopping profile
focusing on travel, books,
camping gear, stuff like that.
And there were purchases
designed for cold and snow.
But he lives in Colorado.
That's cold and snowy.
Right, but he also bought travel
books for Taos and Albuquerque
both in New Mexico.
Okay, you may be
onto something.
- We'll look into it.
- Wait. That's not all.
On a hunch, I called the new tenant who
moved into Hazel Haibach's apartment.
I asked her if she'd forgotten
anything, needed it mailed. Turn out she did.
The address she gave
was a P.O. box in Santa Fe.
New Mexico.
At the foot of the Sangre de Cristo
mountains.
- Yeah.
- Great.
Get the satellites
looking in the area.
I'll put in a request to get a drone up.
If they are out there,
I think we can find them.
She got away.
That's my girl.
That's all right.
Bet I can find her.
Get back out to the car.
Richard's coming.
Hey, do you think it was by chance
that I picked you up?
That told me
when you escaped.
I was coming for you, stupid.
We think we may have found the place
that Grace Van Pelt is being held.
It's a seasonal cabin up
near the edge of the tree line.
You have evidence of occupation?
Firm evidence?
Smoke coming out of the chimney,
going back six weeks.
Same time Hazel Haibach
left Sacramento.
And there's a gray S.U.V.
parked next to the building.
- It all matches up.
- This must be the place.
Okay.
I'll call the chopper.
We'll be there in an hour.
Pull over and stop.
We're here. Get out.
That's where Grace is?
Get out and see.
And your sister, Hazel, right?
She's there, too?
What?
Well, you didn't think
we knew?
Do we look
that stupid to you?
Shut up
and get out of the car.
No.
Out of the car now.
Think you're a big man,
do you?
You really think I'd let you get away
with what you've done?
I will shoot you
if you don't do what I say.
Believe me.
Go ahead.
I don't think
you have it in you.
Now who looks stupid?
The bullet Rigsby fired next to you
was the only one in the gun.
Not a particularly strong trick,
but it got the job done.
What you're gonna do now
is get your sister
to come out of the house
and put her hands on her head.
Come on. Get out.
Come on.
- Let's go.
- Call out to your sister
and tell her to let Grace go
and come out here.
Hazel?
"Hazel!"
"The police have me."
They say you have
to let the girl go and come out.
"Everything's gonna be fine,
Hazel"
"exactly as your brother says."
No, now you shut up.
No, shut up!
Call out to her again.
Hazel?
I don't know where she is.
Maybe she went out.
Her S.U.V.'s right there.
Hazel!
I don't know where she is.
I don't know.
- That's Grace.
- Rigsby.
- But, Jane, it's Grace.
- Jjust don't panic.
You go.
Be careful.
Stay there.
Grace. It's okay.
Everything's gonna be okay.
I'm gonna
get you out of here.
Where is she?
Behind you!
Nice shot, Hazel!
Don't move.
It's gonna be all right.
I promise.
- Wayne!
- This isn't a trick gun, is it?
- No!
- If I shoot this one
a real bullet will come out,
won't it?
Wayne!
No. No.
No! No, Wayne!
- Wayne?
- Well...
there was at least one.
Let's go have some fun.
Untie her and bring her along.
Come on.
Go on.
Go left.
Left again.
Why so quiet, Mr. Smarty?
Cat got your tongue?
You always have an answer
for everything, usually, don't you?
Go on. Go ahead.
Kneel down.
Right here.
Go ahead.
I thought we could play
a little game.
Like a quiz show.
I'd ask questions...
and you get to keep a finger
for every right answer.
- I'd rather not.
- Okay, first question...
Who's smarter now?
- I don't want to.
- You or me?
I don't... I don't want to.
No answer? Okay.
Wayne!
Wayne. Oh, God, Wayne.
- We need to get to a hospital.
- Yeah.
And then Haibach shot you
a second time?
Yeah. That one hurt.
But you got back up,
disarmed the sister
and stopped Haibach.
Nice work, Wayne.
He said he was gonna save me,
and he did.
You do realize you got shot
with your own gun.
Oh, please, Cho, no jokes.
It hurts when I laugh.
No, I'm just saying, if you tell
that story in the future
you might want to leave
that part out.
Seriously, I'm gonna split a stitch.
We should go,
let you get some rest.
I don't know what we would have
done if we'd lost you.
I knew you guys would come.
Bye.
You two take very good care
of each other.
Didn't mean to interrupt.
Oh, we were, uh...
Just leaving.
Bye.
I wanted to come by and see
how you're doing.
Thank you.
And to let you know that you
impressed the hell out of us.
Not too many people
can do what you did.
Thank you. Really.
We're just glad
that you're both okay.
Yeah.
And if you two ever think about
getting back to our side of the business
give me a call.
I don't think so.
Civilian life, here we come.
Well, that's too bad.
Anyhow, the offer's still open.
- Thank you.
- Take care.
- Bye.
Okay. I'm gonna head out, too.
Oh, don't go yet, buddy.
Got lunch coming up.
I can get you your own.
Hospital lunch?
It's really not that bad.
They got cherry cobbler.
I was really angry
at you for doing what you did
but then I thought better of it.
It was a stupid idea,
but, hey, it worked.
Whoa. Stupid?
Not necessarily stupid.
Simple. Not stupid.
But I am still angry at you
for not telling me
what you were gonna do.
I thought you'd gone nuts.
Oh, come on, please. It's not like I haven't
abducted people before.
It's not funny.
I was really scared.
- I'm sorry.
- No, you're not.
I can tell when
you're not being sincere now.
Well, clearly, you can't,
because I am sorry.
I can tell just by looking
at you, okay?
But you can't see
what I'm feeling.